Today's דף Daf is דף נה. Daf Nun Hey. We had,
before we get into the whole discussion of today's דף, Daf, which
is a very hashkafic one, אגדי, Agadic, which would be fascinating, I
just wanted for one second, you know we had discussed, we had
finished up all the issue about animals and collars and walking your
animals, so I thought I would show you a line or two
from the שמירת שבת כהלכתה Shemiras Shabbos Kehilchasa here. He says like
this.
So in ז Zayin here he says on the right-hand side, וענין
שביתת בהמתו הוא שבעל החיים ידאג כך שלא תצא הבהמה לרשות הרבים
ולא לכרמלית בשעה שמשא על גביה, V'inyan shevisas beheima hu sheba'al hachayim
yidog kach shelo tetzei habeheima l'reshut harabim v'lo l'karmelit b'sha'at shemasa al
gabeha, carrying something. Then he describes what a משא masa is. And
then if you look at ח Ches he says, בהמה שלשם שמירתה
יש ביצואר חבל סביב צוארה, Beheimah she-l'shem shemirata yesh bitzvar chevel saviv
tzavarah, an animal that needs a rope or a collar, מותר לו
להוליכה ברשות הרבים בחבל זה ובלבד שקצהו לא יבלוט טפח אחד או
יותר מתחת יד המוליכה, Muttar lo l'hachircha birshut harabim b'chevel zeh u-v'vad
she-ketzei lo yivlot tefach echad o yoter mitachat yad hamolicho, exactly what
we said yesterday. Right, this is the application, right, so yesterday that
the leash cannot go a טפח tefach or two outside of your
hand. וגם יקפיד שחלק החבל שבו הוא מוליך את הבהמה לא יקרב
כדי טפח אחד סמוך לארץ, V'gam yakpid she-chelek hachevel she-bo hu molich
es habeheimah lo yikarav k'dei tefach echad samuch la-aretz, right, so this
is just basically the פסק psak of the גמרא Gemara but here
you see applied in practical verses. You can walk your dog or
your animal on a leash even in a רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim.
Okay, so you can, but you have to make sure that
the leash does not get within a טפח tefach of the ground,
correct. Okay,
and then he also says, וכשכורך את החבל בשבת סביב צואר הבהמה
יזהר שלא להישען עליה. U-keshe-koreich es hachevel bi-shabbos saviv tzavar habeheimah yizaher
shelo lishaen aleha. This is still assuming that animals are מוקצה, muktzah,
so don't lean on your animal or use your animal somehow because
you're not allowed to use בעלי חיים, ba'alei chayim, what, yes, so
you can walk your dog but don't somehow like use it or
lean on it and so on. Are work animals also מוקצה? muktzah?
No, no, the general assumption is that all animals are מוקצה. muktzah.
There's some discussion nowadays about pets but he is working with the
standard assumption that even pets are מוקצה. muktzah.
Can you pet them?
Yeah, מוקצה muktzah the problem of moving, okay, but there is another
issue about being משתמש mishtamesh in בעלי חיים. ba'alei chayim. Anyway, I
don't want to get into that whole thing. ט, Tet, he says,
because this also came up yesterday about the little red strings on
the chickens or whatever, סימן הכר התלוי על צוארה של בהמה, siman
heker hatalui al tzavarah shel beheima, תג, tag, right, which is to
know who it owns, אינו שמירה רגילה לבהמה, eino shemirah regilah labeheima,
פסקing psak straight the גמרא, Gemara, doesn't assume that the context has
changed that, ואסור להניח לה לצאת בו ברשות הרבים, v'assur lehaniach lah
latzeit bo birshut harabim, you can't have it go out with its
tags. ולפיכך על בעלי כלבים להקפיד שלא להוציא כלביהם במקום שאין עירוב
כשסימן על צואריהם. U'lefichach al ba'alei klavim l'hakpid shelo lehotzi klaveihem b'makom
she-ein eruv k'she-siman al tzavareihem.
So he says you can't have a, right, a tag or a
license. Okay and then at the end he says, the last part
of this is, והוא סימן הכר הקבוע באוזן הבהמה במסמר שעליו מספר
זיהוי ושאר פרטים אינו בכלל זה, V'hu siman heker hakavua b'ozen habeheima
b'masmer she-alav mispar zihui v'sha'ar pratim eino bichlal zeh,
I guess if it would sometimes have like the real thing that
would be, you know, really pinched in or whatever stapled into the
dog or animal, מכיוון שלא ניתן להסירו. mikeivan shelo nitan le-hasiro. If
something really cannot be removed, then it's different.
So anyway, you have like a microchip or something like that.
Anyway, but this extends in most
places dogs have to have tags on, right.
So anyway, I wanted you to see at least here it's being
applied very practically to the issue of pets. I am not going
to discuss that further that was yesterday's דף, daf, but I wanted
you to see that.
I wanted you to see that. Let's go on. Now, the גמרא
Gemara spoke yesterday we're at the bottom of נד עמוד ב, Nun
Dalet Amud Bais, and the גמרא Gemara spoke yesterday about that it
wasn't רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer cow, it was his neighbor's, but he
was held liable, responsible because he didn't do anything about it. And
then it spoke about
if you can protest other
people's misbehavior and you don't, you are held responsible.
So then the גמרא Gemara now continues like this. We'll pick up
from אמר פפא Amar Papa two lines from the bottom on נד
עמוד ב. Nun Dalet Amud Bais. אמר פפא והני דבי ריש גלותא,
Amar Papa v'hanei d'bei Reish Galusa, the members of the house of
the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa that were the political heads and they
could have had ability to intervene with anything that was being done,
נתפסו על כולי עלמא, nispsu al kulei alma, they have the responsibility
for
the whole, they are held responsible for everybody's wrongdoing because they could
have done something about it. כי הא דאמר רבי יוחנן Ki ha
d'amar Rebbe Yochanan like רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said, מאי דכתיב, mai
d'chasiv, what's meant by the פסוק, pasuk, ה' במשפט יבוא עם זקני
עמו ושריו, Hashem b'mishpat yavo im ziknei amo v'sarav,
God will come to judgment with the elders of His nation and
the officers? So elders are understood to be sages. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אם שרים חטאו, im sarim chatu, if the officers sinned,
those were the political heads, so they did wrong, they did not
lead the people properly, top of נה עמוד א, Nun Hey Amud
Aleph, זקנים אם מה חטאו, zekeinim im mah chatu,
what did the elders, what did the sages do wrong? It was
the political heads that did something wrong. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא אימא על זקנים שלא מיחו בשרים, ella eima al zekeinim shelo
michu b'sarim, yes,
God will come in judgment with the elders because they did not
protest against the officers, against the political heads. So the rabbis or
people that have a religious voice that could be heard and are
in a position to protest have responsibility when they remain silent and
they as well are held accountable.
This applies nowadays too?
Presumably. רב יהודה הוה יתיב קמיה דשמואל, Rav Yehuda hava yasiv kamlei
d'Shmuel, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was sitting in front of שמואל. Shmuel.
אתאי ההיא איתתא קצווחה קמיה, Asis hai iteta katzavcha kamei,
a certain woman was coming and she was sort of yelling in
front of him and she was complaining some injustice had been done.
to her. ולא הוה משגח בה, V'lo hava mashgach ba, he paid
her no regard. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said to him, לא סבר ליה מר, Lo savar lei mar, does
the master not hold about the of the verse, אטם אזנו מזעקת
דל, Otem azno mi'za'akat dal,
somebody who seals his ear from the outcry of the poor, גם
הוא יקרא ולא יענה, Gam hu yikra v'lo ye'aneh, he will also
cry out and not be answered? How could you not pay attention
to this poor woman? אמר ליה, Amar lei, so שמואל Shmuel said,
שיננא, Shina'na,
which means like sharp one or, again, it's always a question whether
this is an insult or a compliment, anyway, רישך בקרירי, Reishka b'kriri,
if your head, meaning I, שמואל, Shmuel, am your head, I'm above
you, if I get judged with cold water, רישא דרישך, Reisha d'reishka,
the head of your head, the one who is above me, בחמימי,
B'hamimei, will be judged with scalding water. Meaning, okay, maybe I'm somewhat
responsible to deal with this, but ultimately I'm not the person in
charge here. We'll see in a minute who the person in charge
was, and he is the one that's really not taking care of
these issues, and he's the one that's really going to be held
responsible. So it's not exactly saying that what I'm doing is right,
but there's somebody else who's more responsible here. Now let's take a
look at how the גמרא Gemara continues this. הוה יתיב מר עוקבא,
Ha yasiv Mar Ukva, because מר עוקבא Mar Ukva sitting, right, and
מר עוקבא Mar Ukva a minute ago was, if you remember מר
עוקבא Mar Ukva was mentioned as the cold compress on the on
the sheep. It was said, oh that's treating the sheep like מר
עוקבא. Mar Ukva. So apparently, right, did it say it was treating
the sheep like מר עוקבא? Mar Ukva? Anyway, so מר עוקבא Mar
Ukva was in a real position of authority and he's sitting, and
on בית דין, Beis Din, and he is the head of the
בית דין. Beis Din. דכתיב, D'ksiv, and he's the one that's really
going to be held responsible, because it says, בית דוד כה אמר
ה', Beis David koh amar Hashem, House of David so says God,
דינו לבקר משפט, Dinu laboker mishpat, deal justice in the morning, והצילו
גזול מיד עושק, V'hatzilu gazul miyad oshek, save the one who is
being stolen, who's being robbed from the oppressor, פן תצא כאש חמתי,
Pen tetzei ka'esh hamati, lest like fire goes out my anger, ובערה
ואין מכבה, U'ba'ara v'ein mechabeh, and it will consume and there will
be none that extinguishes it, מפני רע מעלליהם, Mipnei ro'a ma'alaleihem, because
of the evil of their doings. So you בית דוד, Beis David,
the political heads, you are the one that has ability to do
to deal with injustice. If you do not deal with it, you
will be judged with this with my fire, with my anger. So
מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, who's really in the position, he's the real
political head, and he's not doing it, he is going to be
judged with the scalding fire. Me, I'll be judged with cold water.
So, what?
I just want to see the scenario here. All these רבנן Rabbanim
are sitting around, who was there?
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and שמואל Shmuel are sitting around. מר עוקבא
Mar Ukva is not present. He's referring to מר עוקבא. Mar Ukva.
And רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is saying to him, how could you?
This woman is coming complaining and he's basically turning a deaf ear.
It's not clear if they're בית דין Beis Din or whatever, but
right, she's coming to them and they're ignoring her. And רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda is trying to intervene on her behalf. And רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda is saying, how can you not listen to somebody who
is crying out to you? And שמואל Shmuel doesn't really justify his
actions, but he more says, look, the primary responsibility lies with my
boss, מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, he's the real person in charge and
the head of the בית דין, Beis Din, and he's the one,
right, and he wasn't there, but apparently he has not set up
a system that needs
to be in place. And he's the one that's really going to
be judged
harshly. Now again, it doesn't exactly fully it sounds like passing the
buck, but there's truth to that as well. If you're a cog
in a system and the system is not operating properly, very often
there's a limited amount that you're able to do, right? So I
don't know, I wasn't there, I don't know the circumstances, but at
least from what שמואל Shmuel is saying is he's saying, look, I
can only do so much, the real responsibility and the real problem
here lies with מר עוקבא. Mar Ukva. So I understand it's a
little passing the buck, but there could be truth to it as
well. But the point is that certainly it was a pretty harsh
indictment of מר עוקבא Mar Ukva who has a whole that apparently
the whole system is one that does not allow for justice to
be served here. Right, I mean at least to again. What?
It's still the same, this could be written on a bumper sticker.
Right,
exactly. So we will continue with this. But look, I think it's
amazing that at least they're willing to exactly.
Doesn't help the woman.
It doesn't help the woman. So אמר ליה רב זירא לרב סימון,
Amar lei Rav Zeira l'Rav Simon, we're going to continue in this
vein. So said רב זירא Rav Zeira to רב סימון, Rav Simon,
לוכחינו מר להני דבי ריש גלותא, Lochechanu Mar l'hanei d'bei reish galusa,
you
רב סימון, Rav Simon, you should give
remonstrate, תוכחה, hochecha, you know give מוסר mussar to the members of
the house of the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa that they are not
doing what they need to be doing. Either they themselves are acting
incorrectly or they're not intervening and they're not creating a just system.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, לא מקבלי מינאי, lo mekablun minai, what good
is it going to do, they're not going to listen to me.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, אף על גב
דלא מקבלי, Af al gav d'lo mekablun, even though they won't listen
to you, they won't accept your מוסר, mussar, לוכחינו מר, lochechanu mar,
you nevertheless have to give a מוסר, mussar, you have to stand
up and protest.
And why did he protest? Presumably he felt that רב סימון Rav
Simon was in a greater position
for his protest to be heard. And even if you think they
won't listen to you, you have to protest. דאמר רב אחא ברבי
חנינא, D'amar Rav Acha b'rebbe Hanina, because רב אחא Rav Acha said
in the name of רבי חנינא, Rebbe Hanina, מעולם לא יצתה מדה
טובה מפי הקדוש ברוך הוא וחזר בה לרעה, Me'olam lo yatzta midda
tova mipi Hakadosh Baruch Hu v'chazar bah l'ra'ah, never a good decree
went out from the mouth of the Holy One Blessed Be He
and he retracted it for a bad one. came from the mouth
of God and went back for evil meaning God never took back
a good promise חוץ מדבר זה Chutz midavar zeh except for one
thing דכתיב. Dechtiv. By the way, this is an important principle for
רמב״ם Rambam because רמב״ם Rambam says how does a נביא navi prove
that he's a true נביא? navi? He prophesies something and it comes
true. But the גמרא Gemara says but sometimes we see that God
reverses himself, right? Like God says he'll wipe out ננוה Nineveh and
then he doesn't wipe out ננוה. Nineveh. So even if it doesn't
come true, you don't know that he's not a false נביא. navi.
So the רמב״ם Rambam says yes, God will take back a bad
prediction, a bad prophecy if people do תשובה, teshuva, but something that
God promises for good, that God won't reverse himself. So the פשט
pshat that the גמרא Gemara is saying that God has never said
something for good and taken it back with one exception חוץ מדבר
זה Chutz midavar zeh דכתיב Dechtiv ויאמר ה' אליו Vayomer Hashem elav
God said to him. This is a story in יחזקאל Yechezkel prophesying
the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. יחזקאל Yechezkel went into
exile a few years, about ten years before the destruction of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And in about these three chapters of 8
through 10 in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, he prophesies first of all, it's a
famous story about you might remember about people worshipping עבודה זרה avodah
zarah in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, people turning their back in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to the Holy of Holies and defecating.
So he describes all of these terrible sins, also about people doing
injustice. It's not just ritual sin, injustice. And then he says a
vision of these angels or these people that are going to come
into ירושלים Yerushalayim and wipe out all the people. But it says
one man was amongst them in this vision dressed in linen, and
he was given the commandment to put a mark on the foreheads
of the righteous so that the righteous would be protected when all
of ירושלים Yerushalayim would be destroyed. Okay, so that's the prophecy. So
let's take a look. ויאמר ה' אליו Vayomer Hashem elav God said
to this man dressed in linen
עבר בתוך העיר בתוך ירושלים Avor betoch hair betoch Yerushalayim pass through
the city, through Jerusalem והתוית תו Vehitvita tav and place a
mark, תו, tav, the גמרא Gemara will later explain that literally means
a תו, tav, the letter תו. tav. Anyway, make a mark על
מצחות האנשים הנאנחים והנאנקים על כל התועבות הנעשות בתוכה Al mitzchot ha'anashim
hane'enachim vehane'enakim al kol hato'evot hana'asot betocha on the foreheads of all
the people that are moaning and groaning because of all the abominations,
the righteous people who bemoan the abominations. Put a mark on their
head, they will be saved and protected when the city is destroyed.
אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא לגבריאל Amar lei Hakadosh Baruch Hu leGavriel
so now the גמרא Gemara takes over. So here's what happened. God
said to גבריאל. Gavriel.
So אליו elav is גבריאל? Gavriel?
Yes, אליו elav right, the גמרא Gemara understands that the person in
linen, the angel in linen, is גבריאל. Gavriel. So God said to
גבריאל Gavriel לכי ורשמי על מצחן של צדיקים תו של דיו Lechi
verishmi al mitzchan shel tzadikim tav shel d'yo
go mark on the foreheads of the צדיקים tzadikim a mark or
the letter תו tav out of ink שלא ישלטו בהם מלאכי חבלה
Shelo yishletu bahem malachei chabala the angels of destruction who we will
see be referenced in another פסוק. pasuk. When they wipe out ירושלים
Yerushalayim will not have control over the צדיקים. tzadikim. ועל מצחן של
רשעים Ve'al mitzchan shel resha'im now this is not in the פסוק.
pasuk. The פסוק pasuk only mentions a mark on the forehead of
the צדיקים, tzadikim, but the גמרא Gemara now completes the sort of
creates a parallel. Make a mark on the forehead of the רשעים
resha'im תו של דם tav shel dam a mark or a תו
tav of blood כדי שישלטו בהן מלאכי חבלה Kedei sheyishletu bahen malachei
chabala so the angels of destruction actually can go ahead and destroy
them. אמרה מידת הדין לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא Amra midat hadin lifnei
Hakadosh Baruch Hu so now that sounds like it is מידת הדין,
midat hadin, right? You kill the wicked and you don't kill the
righteous and maybe you think that the מידת הרחמים midas harachamim would
now try to intervene. But no, the מידת הדין midat hadin is
saying that's not דין. din. Says the מידת הדין midat hadin before
God ריבונו של עולם Ribono shel olam Master of the Universe מה
נשתנו אלו מאלו Ma nishtanu elu me'elu why are you treating the
צדיקים tzadikim different than the רשעים? resha'im? So אמר לה amar lah
what do you mean? הללו צדיקים גמורים והללו רשעים גמורים Halalu tzadikim
gemurim vehalalu resha'im gemurim these are righteous, fully righteous, these are fully
wicked. אמרה לפניו Amra lefanav so the attribute of justice said ריבונו
של עולם Ribono shel olam Master of the Universe היה בידם למחות
ולא מיחו Haya beyadam limchot velo michu don't let the צדיקים tzadikim
get off. They could have protested, they were in a position to
have done something, and they didn't protest. They're equally responsible. So אמר
לה amar lah so God said to the מידת הדין midat hadin
גלוי וידוע לפני Galuy ve'yadu'a lefanai I, it's well known to me,
it's revealed before me שאם מיחו בהם לא יקבלו מהם She'im michu
bahem lo yikablu mehem even had they protested, they wouldn't have listened.
So you can't hold them responsible. אמרה לפניו Amra lefanav so said
to God ריבונו של עולם Ribono shel olam Master of the Universe
אם לפניך גלוי להם מי גלוי Im lefanecha galuy lahem mi galuy
if it's revealed to you, it's not revealed to them. They still
had a responsibility, they didn't live up to their responsibility. It doesn't
matter whether you knew whether it could have done good or not.
Their
silence, they are held accountable. והיינו דכתיב Vehaynu dechtiv so therefore God
reversed himself, the one time God reversed himself. By the way, the
מהרש״א Maharsha explains if it had just been partly based on the
previous גמרא Gemara that says
if they could have protested for the entire city they're held accountable
for the entire city. Says if it was their own personal sin,
so their own righteousness would have outweighed a personal sin, but they're
actually being held accountable for the sins of thousands. So therefore God
had to reverse himself because now the sins of the thousands which
they are being held accountable for outweighs their own righteousness. So God
said to והיינו דכתיב Vehaynu dechtiv that's what's meant by the verse
זקן בחור ובתולה טף ונשים Zaken bachur uvetula taf venashim wipe them
all out, elder and
young,
virgin or young woman,
infants and women תהרגו למשחית tahar'gu lemashchit destroy. destroy them for destruction.
ועל *ve'al*, so it says, זקן *zaken*, which is an elder, which
is normally understood to be a sage, like we said before, even
like the righteous ones. But then as the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* does
end and this because this is not פשט pshat, *pshat* of the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. פשט *pshat* of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* is the
righteous were saved. The אגדתא Aggadeta. *agadata* is that God reversed himself
and the righteous were wiped out. So the end of the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* says, ועל כל איש ish אשר עליו התו אל תגשו
*ve'al kol ish asher alav hatav al tigshu*, any person that has
the mark don't draw near, וממקדשי תחלו *umimikdashi tachello*, begin the destruction
from the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. So again the end of the
verse sounds like they were protected, but we'll see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* does with it. וכתיב ויחלו באנשים הזקנים אשר לפני הבית
*vechtiv vayachelu ba'anashim hazkeinim asher lifnei habayit*, that God it started with
the elders again understood to be the sages and therefore you know
the ones who would have been the righteous ones nevertheless it began
with them. They were the ones that were first held accountable because
they were in a position to know better and in a position
to do something about it. תני רב Rav יוסף *Tani Rav Yosef*,
so what do you so רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* said, אל תקרי
ממקדשי *al tikrei mimikdashi*, don't read it start from my sanctuary, אלא
Ella, ממקודשי *ela mimikudashai*, start from those that are sanctified to me.
Start from the righteous. אלו בני אדם שקיימו את התורה כולה מאלף
ועד תיו *eilu bnei adam shekiyemu es hatorah kullah me'aleph ve'ad tav*,
those are the people that did the entire תורה Torah *Torah* from
אלף *aleph* to תיו *tav*, here's a play on the word תו
*tav*, a mark and תיו *tav*, okay, they are the ones you
should start from. So what do you do with the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* that says don't do the righteous people? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says that's where God reversed himself. First it said don't do the
righteous people and then the end of the verse says and start
from מקדשי *mikdashai* which is מקודשי *mikudashai* after the מידת הדין midas
hadin. *middas hadin* intervened. And therefore the righteous people as well were
destroyed. ומיד *umiyad*, and immediately, והנה ששה אנשים באים
מדרך שער העליון *vehinei shishah anashim ba'im miderech shaar ha'elyon*, six people
came from the upper gate, אשר מפנה צפונה *asher mifneh tzafonah*, that
turns to the north, ואיש כלי מפצו בידו *ve'ish kli mapatzo beyado*,
each man the instruments of destruction were in his hands. So these
were the מלאכי חבלה *malachei chabalah*, the angels of destruction. ואיש אשר
בתוכם לבוש הבדים *ve'ish asher besocham levush habadim*, this is actually an
earlier פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* when it introduces the setting. You had the
six angels of destruction and the one man dressed in linen that
was what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said is גבריאל *Gavriel*, the angel
who was going to make the marks, וקסת הסופר במתניו *vekeses hasofer
bemosnav*, he had the sort of like the you know right the
the quill or the box for the quills of the scribe on
his loins because he has the he's going to make the marks
on the foreheads. ויבאו ויעמדו אצל מזבח הנחשת *vayavo'u vaya'amdu eitzel mizbeach
hanechoshes*, and they stood by the by the by the copper altar.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* intervenes, מזבח הנחשת מי הוה *mizbeach
hanechoshes mi havah*, there wasn't a copper altar at that time. That
was of the time of משה Moshe, *Moshe*. By the time of
שלמה *Shlomo* they had a they had a stone altar. So אמר
Amar, לו הקדוש ברוך הוא *amar lo hakadosh baruch hu*, so again
we're saying God is saying to them, התחילו ממקום שאומרים שירה לפני
*hatchilu mimakom she'omrim shirah lefanai*, begin from the where they say song
before me, meaning נחשת *nechoshes* is meaning is understood to mean the
the musical instruments that the לויים *Levi'im* use that are that are
made out of metals and made out of copper. So again נחשת
*nechoshes*, yeah, what can I do. Anyway again an indication about starting
from those that should have been most close to me and were
in the greatest position to know better and in a position to
say something about it. ומאן נינהו ששה אנשים *uman ninhu shishah anashim*,
and so who were these six people? We identified the the man
in linen as גבריאל *Gavriel*. Who are the six people who are
going to destroy it? They weren't again people. So אמר רב Amar
Rav חסדא *amar Rav Chisda*, here's what רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says:
קצף אף וחמה ומשחית ומשבר ומכלה *ketzef, aph, vechemah, umashchit, umeshaber, umachleh*.
So I don't know if he's saying that these are their names
or their attributes, but clearly these are angels of destruction. You know,
anger, I don't know, another word for anger, anger, three angers. משחית
*mashchit*, what? Fury, anger.
This is like something right out of Dante.
Right, I well, or or what is it the okay I won't
say it. ומשחית *umashchit* destroyer and breaker and wiper out. Right, הגדה
*agaddah* exactly where you count each descriptor separately. Step and a bit,
annihilate. Annihilator, right. Okay, ומאי שנא תו *umai shna tav*, so why
was it the letter תו *tav*? So אמר רב *amar Rav*, תו
תחיה תו תמות *tav tichyeh, tav tamus*. A תו *tav* means to
live so that was on the righteous and a תו *tav* was
also on the wicked which means they should תו *tav* that's it,
תו *tav* was on the wicked that means that they should die.
So that's very interesting. How do you know the difference? So maybe
one was in blood and the other was ink. But it's like
you know so somebody's marking up their dishes so he puts an
M for מילכיק *milchik* right, and an M for meat right. So
anyway, alright, so anyway. But the different colors. Anyway, so but I
think the point here maybe is exactly playing into the theme which
is there's very little difference, right? It's not like these have the
mark and these don't, these were righteous. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying if you could have done something about it and you're accountable
then there's very little difference between you and the other and the
others. So it's the exact same letter תו תחיה תו תמות *tav
tichyeh, tav tamus*. ושמואל אמר תמה זכות אבות uShmuel amar tama zechut
avot. *u'Shmuel amar tamah zechus avos*. שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says no, it
means that the merit of the of the fathers had ended and
therefore they would not be saved by the merit of the forefathers.
We'll get back to that point in a minute. רבי יוחנן אמר
Rabbi Yochanan amar תחון זכות אבות zechus avos *Rabbi Yochanan amar tachon
zechus avos*. The merit of the fathers should rest upon them. So
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says what does this mean, let me just see
the רש"י Rashi. *Rashi*...
No, anyway, it wasn't רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*, it was I think I
was thinking about, I think I was thinking about the מהרש"א Maharsha
*Maharsha*. The מהרש"א *Maharsha* says something like either it's the merit of
the forefathers has ended but the righteous before they got held accountable
because of מידת הדין *Middat ha-Din*. The way the מהרש"א *Maharsha* reads
it is, okay, nobody is going to hear on the merit of
אבות avos, *Avot*, but the righteous still might be able to be
protected for their own merit and then that got reversed. And רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, the way the מהרש"א *Maharsha* reads it, says no,
the merit of the אבות avos *Avot* should help to protect them,
again, not presumably the wicked, but at least the righteous. ריש לקיש
אמר *Reish Lakish amar*, yes?
A strange question because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* never claimed that it
was actually a letter ת *Tav* written on...
it took it for granted. It assumed that the phrase והתוית תו
*v'hitvita tav* did not just mean make a mark but it read
the word תו *Tav* as ת *Tav*. The פסוק *pasuk* says make
a תו *Tav* and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just chose to read
it as ת *Tav* without even saying it was reading it that
way. What do you want me to tell you? That's the assumption
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* brings in. Okay. ריש לקיש אמר *Reish Lakish
amar*, תו סוף חותמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא *Tav sof chotamo shel
HaKadosh Baruch Hu*. ת *Tav* is the end of God's seal. דאמר
רב חנינא חותמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא אמת *D'amar Rav Chanina chotamo
shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu emet*. God's seal is אמת *emet*, is truth,
right? For the רמב"ם *Rambam*, his sort of philosophical, you know, idea
of sort of Greek philosophy that God is like the... the way
the רמב"ם *Rambam* begins his משנה תורה Torah *Mishneh Torah*, you know,
God is, he says God is the first cause and there's... and
everything else only exists because of the truth of God's existence. God
is the only thing that is, you know, is the thing that
has ultimate existence. Everything else's existence is only, you know, contingent and
dependent. So there's like, you know, so God is ultimate truth, you
know. So that's sort of like in the existential sense, but also
obviously in the sense that God's word is true. So the end
of that is the ת *Tav*, so that means like this was
the finality of the seal of God, you know, that this was
what
was
the judgment
that was going to be done. Now,
רש"י *Rashi*, again it's interesting, I'll just digress for a minute, because
רש"י *Rashi*, just take a look at רש"י *Rashi*, חותמו של הקדוש
ברוך הוא אמת *chotamo shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu emet*, about 20 lines
from the bottom, רש"י *Rashi* says, אמצעי לאותיות וראשון ואחרון *emtza'i l'otiyot
v'rishon v'acharon*. All right, so the מ *Mem* is the middle of
the אלף בית *Aleph-Bet*, the א *Aleph* is the first and the
ת *Tav* is the last, so אמת *emet* is, you know, has
the greatest, like the strongest foundation, it's also beginning, middle and end.
So רש"י *Rashi* says, משום אני ראשון ואני אחרון ואני הוא *mishum
ani rishon v'ani acharon v'ani hu*. I am first, I am last
and I am the one. So God is
fully, you know, all-existent, and the truth of all existence. So anyway,
that's what רש"י *Rashi* says, but the רבנו נסים גאון *Rabbeinu Nissim
Gaon*, I mentioned this once before, like we take for granted when
רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* make reference to other sources, but
you know, this whole idea of cross-referencing all of גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
and all of ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* or whatever, you know, didn't come out
of nowhere. So if you look a few generations earlier, רבנו נסים
גאון *Rabbeinu Nissim Gaon* on the left hand side, he says the
following, דאמר רב חנינא חותמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא אמת *d'amar Rav
Chanina chotamo shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu emet*. He says, תמצא עיקר דברי
רב חנינא פרק בא לו כהן גדול במסכת יומא פרק בא לו
*timtza ikar divrei Rav Chanina perek ba lo kohen gadol b'masechet yoma
perek ba lo* and then he says ובתלמוד ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
מסכת סנהדרין אמרו בדרך זה טעם נאה ביותר *u'b'talmud eretz yisrael masechet
sanhedrin amru b'derech zeh ta'am na'eh b'yoter*. I found in the ירושלמי
*Yerushalmi* in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* a very beautiful explanation for this. ונראה לי
לכתבה הנה *v'nir'eh li l'kotvah henah*, and I want to write it
here. והכי אמרו מה חותמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא *v'hachi amru, mah
chotamo shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu*? What's God's seal? רב ביבי בשם רבי
ראובן Reuven, אמר אמת *Rav Bibi b'shem Rabbi Reuven amar emet*. מה
הוא אמת *mah hu emet*? Why is אמת *emet* God's seal? אמר
רב אבא שהוא אלהים חיים ומלך עולם *amar Rav Abba shehu elohim
chayim u'melech olam*. Like, you know, like the truth of all existence,
the God that exists forever. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש אלף ראשא
דאלפביתא מם באמצעיתא ותו בסופא *amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish aleph rosha
d'alphabeta mem b'emtzeita v'tav b'sofa*. לומר אני ראשון שלא קיבלתי מלכות *lomar
ani rishon shelo kibaliti malchut* and so on.
So basically רש"י *Rashi* gets it from a ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, but I
just want you to see it's very nice, like this sort of,
you know, the joy of discovery before everything was so cross-referenced, oh
wait, I got this great ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* I found that explains this
very nicely. Okay, so that is the seal of God, and this
is also maybe underscoring that this was מידת הדין *middat ha-din* and
this was the right justice. So that's the תו *Tav* is the
end of God's seal. אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אלו בני אדם
שקיימו את התורה כולה מאלף ועד תו *amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani
eilu b'nei adam she-kiymu et ha-torah kullah m'aleph v'ad tav*. Like we
said before, no, the completely righteous, they did the entire תורה Torah,
*Torah* from א *Aleph* to ת *Tav*, and nevertheless, they were held
accountable. Now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is going to get onto the
issue of זכות אבות zechus avos *zechut avot*, but it is worth,
you know, just stopping and saying that obviously that's a, you know,
extremely strong indictment. I mean, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is really about
this sense of accountability when you're in a position, and particularly pointing
to themselves, as we saw from the previous story. If you can
make a religious voice and a moral voice and you have to
stand up when injustice is being done. And even if it seems
like it'll do no good, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, you don't
know, and you never know, and you have to protest because who
knows, maybe it will do some good. Now תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* refers
to another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that says that there are times you
don't protest because מוטב שיהיו שוגגין mutav sheyehu shogegin? *mutav she-yihyu shogegin*,
better people should do sin inadvertently than sin intentionally. So תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot* says, well, the difference is, we only say don't sin if
there's absolute no question that they won't... don't protest... take a look.
תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* says, let's read it, ואף על פי דלא
מקבלי להו *v'af al pi
d'lo mitchabli l'homa*, the first תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*. He says, היינו היכא
דספק
אי מקבלי *hainu heicha d'safek i mekablei*. That's only if there's some
doubt that maybe they'll... body agrees to that. The simple sense of
this גמרא Gemara is you never know. You might they might have
thought that there was no chance they would be listened to. That's
still not an excuse. You never know. You can never so when
do you you know you always have to protest maybe you'll maybe
it'll make a difference. So what about the גמרא Gemara, מוטב שיהיו
שוגגין? mutav sheyehu shogegin Well there's some big differences. First of all
מוטב שיהיו שוגגין mutav sheyehu shogegin is about a concern of an
individual. Better you know if it's here you have a whole city
that's wicked and so on number one and as opposed to a
particular individual. The second issue is you could maybe say מוטב שיהיו
שוגגין mutav sheyehu shogegin well maybe it makes you have more responsibility
to do something when it's a wide group of people and not
just an individual sin. Number two is is that מוטב שיהיו שוגגין
mutav sheyehu shogegin. is about you could say it by like ritual
sins. If you're doing something wrong on שבת Shabbos and you're not
going to listen to me anyway I shouldn't say anything. If the
sins are between בין אדם לחברו bein adam l'chaveiro you can't say
מוטב שיהיו שוגגין. mutav sheyehu shogegin There are people that are actually
suffering as a result of the injustice. Right, so I can't say
I don't want you to be held accountable for doing it willfully.
I have to protect this innocent person who's suffering as a result
of your actions. Also מוטב שיהיו שוגגין mutav sheyehu shogegin according to
some only applies it does not apply if it's an obvious sin.
If it's you know therefore if it's explicit in the תורה don't
steal, don't murder or whatever it says, keep שבת, Shabbos, you don't
say you know if it's well maybe the details aren't obvious. Anyway,
you don't say מוטב שיהיו שוגגין if it's something obvious. You still
have to protest. And I want to say one final thing about
this which is the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like you always
protest because you never know. But it's also worth noting that there's
even a value to protest even if it won't do any good.
Because you have exactly if if you're silent when injustice or when
something you know wrong is being done then it seems like you
are you know that you know
complicit in it, that you're okay with it, that you're not offended
by it. By by raising a voice of protest even if nobody
listens, nobody changes their ways, it at least says this is not
acceptable. You know and it holds out you know the standards that
we're supposed to be abiding by and it defends those standards even
if it doesn't change anybody's actions. Exactly. Exactly, silence is like admission.
So this is a very powerful
we just talked about right before חנוכה. Chanukah. Yeah.
With with all the Hellenistic Jews
and not enough protest within the community. Right, although a lot of
Hellenistic Jews were very willing participants not just that they were right.
Right, but this is the people that know better but don't feel
it'll do any good and you still have to protest. Right. Right,
and this whole thing started with the case where the woman right
is begging for help. She's coming to and she's being ignored. And
she's crying and they're ignoring her. So that's not a case of
we don't know if she'll be she asked. I know, which is
why I mean שמואל a little bit passed the buck or you
could say a lot passed the buck but nevertheless you know saying
yeah we're obviously this is wrong and I mean he said מר
עוקבא Mar Ukva is going to be judged in scalding water you
know so it wasn't so nobody was defending the action.
No but he still didn't help the woman. Right but again you
don't know from the case it sounds the way I read it
and again maybe you'll say it's apologetic is is that he you
know if you're within a system you sometimes have a limited amount
of the control over what you can do. I see this all
the time. I I understand. Right. And and the rabbis act the
same way.
They they will not do anything about injustice. The women are crying
begging for help and they're being being ignored. Yeah. So you have
you have to now blazon this גמרא Gemara you know okay. Right.
So now let's see so that's in terms of protesting.
Obviously very critical.
Now the גמרא Gemara continues says the following.
Okay. ואימתי תמה זכות אבות? V'emasai tamu zechus avos? So we said
before that one reading of it was the merit of the forefathers
had ended. So the גמרא Gemara says when did the merit of
the forefathers end?
So אמר רב said רב מימיו של הושע בן בארי miyamoso shel
Hoshea ben Beeri from the time of the נביא Navi of הושע.
Hoshea. שנאמר אגלה את נבלותה לעיני מאהביה. Shene'emar egaleh es nevalusah l'einei
me'ahaveha. I will reveal its abomination to the eyes of its lover
which could mean here the you know ירושלים Yerushalayim and ישראל Yisrael
is described as as the woman and and the lover is you
know all those מאהביה me'ahaveha here could actually be some say that
this might mean the אבות, avos you know it'll be that the
that the abomination will be revealed ואיש לא יצילנה מידי. v'ish lo
yatzilenah miyadi. But whatever it means God says I will you know
I will expose her nakedness and you know I will obviously bring
destruction on ירושלים Yerushalayim on ישראל Yisrael and nobody will save her
from me. So nobody will save her even the אבות avos. won't
be able to save save her from here on in you know
they'll go and and therefore the אבות avos. were no longer the
זכות אבות zechus avos. was no longer operative. ושמואל אמר מימי חזאל
U'Shmuel amar miyamei Chazael from the time of חזאל Chazael which was
the king of ארם Aram at the end of the period of
the בית ראשון. Bayis Rishon. שנאמר חזאל מלך ארם לחץ את ישראל
כל ימי יהואחז. Shene'emar Chazael melech Aram lachatz es Yisrael kol yemei
Yehoachaz. So he pressured ישראל, Yisrael, he was you know afflicted them.
וכתיב ויחן ה' אותם וירחמם ויפן אליהם למען בריתו את אברהם יצחק
ויעקב ולא אבה השחיתם ולא השליכם מעל פניו עד עתה. U'chsiv vayachan
Hashem osam vayerachamem vayifen aleihem lemaan briso es Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov v'lo
avah hashchisam v'lo hishlicham me'al panav ad atah. God had compassion on
them and he had compassion for the sake of his covenant with
אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov and he did not want to
destroy them and did not cast them away until now. So רש"י
says as good until now the זכות אבות zechus avos, worked, the
ברית bris worked. From here on in... It's not going to do
any good. One minute, רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
אומר omer מימי אליהו. mimei Eliyahu. No, it wasn't the end of
the בית ראשון, bayis rishon, it was much earlier than that it
ran out. From the time of אליהו Eliyahu already, שנאמר shenemar ויהי
בעלות המנחה ויגש אליהו הנביא ויאמר השם אלוהי אברהם יצחק וישראל. vayehi
baalot hamincha vayigash Eliyahu hanavi vayomar Hashem Elohei Avraham Yitzchak veYisrael. God,
right when he was fighting with the prophets of the Baal, God,
King of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, היום יודע hayom yivada let it
be known today כי אתה אלוהים בישראל ki ata Elohim beYisrael you
are the God of Israel ואני עבדך ובדברך עשיתי את כל הדברים
האלה vaani avdecha uvdivarcha asiti et kol hadevarim haele I am your
servant, I did it with your word. So now where do you
see that that was that that was ended there? Because this היום
יודע hayom yivada today it'll be known, after today, you know, no
longer rely on the זכות אבות. zechus avos And he specifically mentioned
Abraham, Isaac, and Israel. אלוהי אברהם יצחק וישראל. Elohei Avraham Yitzchak veYisrael.
רבי יוחנן אמר מימי חזקיהו mimei Chizkiyahu from the time of Chizkiyahu,
שנאמר shenemar למרבה המשרה ולשלום אין קץ lemarbe hamisra uleshalom ein ketz
for the great of sort of, you know, what is משרה? misra?
Dominion and anyway, and for peace without end על כסא דוד ועל
ממלכתו להכין אותה ולסעדה במשפט ובצדקה al kisei David veal mamlachto lehachin
ota ulesada bemishpat uvitzedaka on the chair of David, on his kingdom,
with justice and righteousness מעתה ועד עולם meata vead olam from here
on in it's going to be only מידת הדין. You don't benefit
from the זכות אבות, zechus avos. it's only משפט וצדקה. mishpat utzedaka.
קנאת השם צבאות תעשה זאת. kinat Hashem Tzevaos taase zos. So here
you have a גמרא Gemara basically saying that the זכות אבות zechus
avos ended and the only question is when did it end. Now
this is obviously very difficult and has been very challenging to later
commentators because we're always praying, right, אלוהי אברהם יצחק ויעקב Elohei Avraham
Yitzchak veYaakov with the first תפילה tefilla in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
is אבות. avos, You know, it seems like we're always sort of
invoking the זכות אבות. zechus avos So if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafos ושמואל אמר תמה זכות אבות. tama zechus avos תוספות
Tosafos says אמר רבנו תם דזכות אבות תמה אבל ברית אבות לא
תמה. amar Rabbeinu Tam dezchus avos tama aval bris avos lo tama.
So meaning the merit ended, not the ברית. bris. Now presumably the
difference is is that the ברית bris means God is committed to
us, right, he made a promise, he's going to protect us, he's
our God, right, that doesn't get reversed. What the זכות אבות zechus
avos. means that they, you know, earned up all of this like
brownie points, all of this credit, and we're still living off of
like you inherited a, you know, you inherited a, you know, a
fund, like what is it called, a trust fund. So we've been
living off of the trust fund but, you know, so our deeds
have not allowed us to just live off of the interest, we've
had to cut into the principle. So over many many years there's
nothing left in the trust fund so we're no longer benefiting from
all of their זכות, zechus, you know, so we have to live
on our own זכות. zechut. But God is still committed to us
for the sake of the אבות. avot One minute, that is what
תוספות Tosafot says. If you look at the end of תוספות, Tosafot
תוספות Tosafot also tries to say maybe the זכות אבות zechus avos
only ended for the רשעים, reshaim, maybe it's still there for the
צדיקים, tzaddikim, splitting who gets what זכות אבות. zechus avos. And then
תוספות Tosafot says at the end ועל זה אנו סומכים להזכיר זכות
אבות. veal ze anu somchim lehazkir zechus avos. That's why we mention
it, that we, you know, we believe that there's still a זכות
אבות zechus avos at least for the, you know, at least for
those that merit it. ובשלהי ויקרא רבה רדא אמר uveshiley Vayikra Rabba
Rada amar לעולם זכות אבות קיימת leolam zechus avos kayemet ולעולם אנו
מזכירים אותה. uleolam anu mazkirim ota. שנאמר shenemar כי אל רחום ולא
ישכח את ברית אבותיך. ki el rachum velo yishkach es bris avosecha.
So not a distinguish between זכות zechus and ברית, bris, but to
say that it's always around. Disagrees, other opinions, I just wanted to
show you quickly, we don't have that much time, but I made
some, you know, I printed up some interesting sources on זכות אבות.
zechus avos. So I will just, I will summarize them for you
and read maybe one or two lines. So the רמב״ן Ramban on
the תורה basically says that, so the end of the first line
here from the רמב״ן Ramban is כי בגלותנו עתה תמה זכות אבות.
ki begalusenu ata tama zechus avos. So he says in our, in
our exile now there's no longer זכות אבות zechus avos ואין לנו
הצלה מיד העמים. veein lanu hatzala miyad haamim. The only thing that
saves us, he doesn't say it's ברית אבות, bris avos, תוספות Tosafot,
would have said it's ברית אבות, bris avos, רק בעבור שמו. rak
baavur shemo. God does it to protect his holy name, that if
the, that if we would be destroyed, then that people would say,
you know, not believe in God and God's promises. So he doesn't
mean to say it's the ברית אבות, bris avos, nothing is to
protect us. The טור Tur which is also sort of the ספרד
Sefarad world, he basically says that's the ברכה beracha we make, the
first ברכה beracha of אבות, avot, we actually say ומביא גואל לבני
בניהם למען שמו. umevi goel livnei veneihem lemaan shemo. God brings a
redeemer to the children for God's sake, it's no longer for the
זכות אבות. zechus avos. Even if the זכות אבות zechut avot, we
can't rely on, you know, at least do it למען שמו. lemaan
shemo. Now רש״י Rashi very interestingly on the פסוק where God reveals
the י״ג מידות, yud gimmel middos, רש״י Rashi tries to restore the
balance a little. Right, ויאמר אני אעביר כל טובי vayomar ani aavir
kol tuvi it's the third paragraph here, הגיע שעה שתראה בכבודי מה
שאתה צריך להזכיר בעת חרון אף higia shaa shetareh bichvodi ma sheata
tzarich lehazkir bees charon af I will allow you to see, ולפי
שאני רוצה ללמדך סדר תפילה ulefi sheani rotze lelamdecha seder tefilla I
have to teach you the way of prayer, כשנצרכת לבקש רחמים על
ישראל הזכירו לי זכות אבות. keshenitzrachta levakesh rachamim al Yisrael hazkiru li
zechus avos. When you need to ask for compassion, mention the זכות
אבות. zechut avot. קסברת דמשה kasavarta de-Moshe maybe you think, משה, Moshe
maybe you think that if תמה tamah, זכות אבות zechut avot, it
would run out there'd be no hope? So אני אעביר כל מידת
טובי ani aavir kol middas tuvi I'm going to tell you the
י״ג מידות yud gimmel middos and that's another way you can get
me to be compassionate. God already anticipated that problem and gave us
an alternative. Okay, so anyway, so the מחזור ויטרי Machzor Vitry which
is from רש"י's school also sort of says, no, of course we
have זכות אבות, zechut avot we rule like that other opinion that's
in the whatever, that's in the מדרש Midrash that תוספות Tosafot quotes.
The רב"יה Raviyah also אשכנזי Ashkenazi is fascinating, the אשכנזים Ashkenazim are
more pushing that we have זכות zechut אבות. avot I don't know
what the exact logic of that difference is. Anyway the רב"יה Raviyah
says, תמה זכות אבות פירוש אינה מסייע מאליה. tamah zechut avot perush
einah mesayaya me'eleyah. It doesn't do it by itself. ומי שציבור או
יחיד שמתפללים עליהם זכור לנו ברית אבות אפשר שתשמע תפילתם. Umi she'tzibbur
o yachid she'mitpallelim aleihem zechor lanu berit avot efshar she'tishma tefillatam. When
we invoke it, that's different. It doesn't work without being invoked. Okay,
so all of these nuances. And I had to end though with
the שפת אמת Sfat Emet because the שפת אמת Sfat Emet says,
first of all he says, okay, maybe we don't have זכות zechut
אבות, avot, we can't get all the way back to אברהם יצחק
ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov which you just did. But we have the
זכות zechut of the שבטים shevatim or we have the זכות zechut
he says of the שבעים נפש shivim nefesh that came down to
מצרים, Mitzrayim, you know, they are the vehicle through which we get
the זכות zechut of the earlier generations, you know, even if the
אבות are too distant from us. So he has some explanations like
that. But the most beautiful which Rivka I had you in mind
when I saw this and when I put it down. Look at
the second paragraph to the left, what he says by ויקרא, Vayikra,
he says like this. He says ויש לדרוש מדלג על ההרים מקפץ
על הגבעות על גאולת עתיד, V'yesh lidrosh medalleg al he'harim mekapeitz al
ha'gevaot al geulat atid, right? That's the פסוק of שיר השירים. Shir
HaShirim. ויתקיים לנו במהרה מאמר מקפץ על הגבעות V'yitkayyem lanu bimherah ma'amar
mekapeitz al ha'gevaot that God will jump on the mountains. גם הרים
הם אבות, Gam harim hem avot, it's true that the mountains are
the אבות, וגבעות הן זכות אמהות. u'gevaot hen zechut immahot. והנשים רחמנים
ביותר, V'hanashim rachmanim beyoter, רחמניות rachmaniyot I guess, כמו שכתבו חז"ל ששלחו
לחולדה הנביאה k'mo shekatvu Chazal she'shalechu l'Chuldah ha'Neviah to get a good
prophecy because women have compassion and they'll see things through that light.
כן יעשה לנו אתה בזכות אמהות לכן גם למאן דאמר תמה זכות
אבות זכות אמהות לא תמה. Ken ya'aseh lanu atah b'zechut immahot lachem
gam le'man d'amar tamah zechut avot zechut immahot lo tamah. You like
that, huh?
So he says the זכות zechut of the mothers, that will save
us in the end. They are more מדת הרחמים. middat harachamim. That's
an interesting. Like רחל Rachel crying? Yeah, exactly. Right? That's in our
literature. What?
Yeah, go ahead, you and Rivka can talk about that offline. Yes,
Jonathan? When I raised my hand, that was my.
You were
going to say זכות אמהות? zechut immahot? There you go. So you
yeah.
Two things. The first three examples were in the northern kingdom, which
had totally evil rulers. The last one was חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu, who was
a good ruler.
But
the גמרא Gemara is not making the distinction. תוספות Tosafot tries to
distinguish between צדיקים tzaddikim and the רשעים. reshaim. I would also say
there's a nice, there's a nice last one to the צדיקים tzaddikim
which is also one of the חסידיק Hasidic masters. He says that
the זכות zechut of the three אבות we've lost, but not the
זכות zechut of אברהם. Avraham. Because אברהם Avraham he says, oh now
I have to read it. He says like this. He says the
פסוק, okay, וזהו והיה כגר בארץ תחילה, v'zehu ve'hayah kager be'eretz techilah,
צריכין להבין למה השויתו הכתוב עם הגרים. tzrichin lehavin lamah hishveto hakatuv
im hagerim. He says like this. אפי' אם יאמרו בגויים שהגרים אינם
מזרעו של יצחק, Afilu im yomru bagoyim she'hagerim einam mizar'o shel Yitzchak,
they're not from the family originally, ואין להזכיר להם עקידתו של יצחק,
v'ein lehazkir lahem akeidato shel Yitzchak, אף על פי כן יצאו זכאי
מפני שהם עם אלוהי אברהם af al pi chen yetzeu zakai mipnei
she'hem am Elohei Avraham שקיבל את הגרים כדאיתא בפרק החגיגה. shekibel et
hagerim ked'ita be'perek ha'Chagigah. ואם כן אברהם V'im ken Avraham is for
all, even for the גרים gerim because אברהם Avraham was the one
you know אב המון גויים av hamon goyim and so on. ואם
כן אף למאן דאמר תמה זכות אבות אבל זכות של אברהם לעולם
עומדת להם לישראל V'im ken af le'man d'amar tamah zechut avot aval
zechut shel Avraham l'olam omedet lahem l'Yisrael לפי שמקרבים עצמם להשם יתברך
בתשובה
ומעשים טובים ונעשים כגרים. lefi she'mekarvim atzmam l'Hashem Yitbarach bitshuvah u'ma'asim tovim
vena'asim k'gerim. So he says אברהם Avraham represents, right, the for the
אב av of the גרים, gerim, the idea of, you know, of
coming close to God, which is what the גר ger did. So
anybody that works to come close to God, even if you don't
have the זכות of the אבות, you have the זכות of אברהם.
Avraham. Yes? If ברית אבות berit avot is no longer in effect,
what does that say about ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. because that's one
of the big points of the ברית? berit?
Right. So that's why תוספות Tosafot I think the distinction of זכות
אבות and ברית אבות berit avot has to be said. You know,
although it's true that some do not make that distinction. Yeah. Right.
Let's keep on. Yes?
Even internally to this גמרא, it says since one opinion is משמואל
mi'Shmuel and yet we see בימי חז"ל bimei Chazal could still invoke
it, so whichever answer you go with even internally to the. Right,
that's a good point. Right, and I think the מהרש"א says that,
that even after it's תמה, you can still invoke it. Okay, now
let's continue. We are not done with the interesting theological issues of
this גמרא. אמר רב אמי אין מיתה בלא חטא ואין יסורין בלא
עון. Amar Rav Ami ein mitah b'lo cheit v'ein yissurin b'lo avon.
There's no death without sin
and there is no affliction without iniquity.
Now where's this you know why is this brought up?
Presumably because the צדיקים tzaddikim died in this גמרא. So the צדיקים
tzaddikim we're saying they died because of they were held accountable because
they could have protested. But you know there's another way to explain
why they died. Right? Because you know in a time of destruction
righteous people suffer and die as well. But he says no, there
is no death without sin and there is no יסורין yissurin without
עון. avon. תוספות by the way says or רש"י. רש"י, no תוספות,
yeah, תוספות says that חטא cheit is an inadvertent sin. עוון avon
is a willful sin.
Now you would have thought ייסור yissur is less
than death but תוספות says no. עוון avon is willful. So there's
no death without at least an inadvertent sin. But there's no affliction
without willful sinning. So that's funny, you would have thought affliction is
less than death, but no, everybody's gotta die. So therefore we're not
say- so you're not going to die blamelessly. There'll be at least
something, even an inadvertent sin, okay, that will sort of, you know,
justify the death or somehow be connected to it. But to get
ייסורין, yissurin, that's only if you've really sinned, that's only עוון. avon.
That's the way at least תוספות reads. Definitely interesting. At some point
someone's... Let's read a little bit more. Okay, so אין מיתה בלא
חטא, ein mita belo cheit, דכתיב הנפש החוטאת היא תמות, dechtiv hanefesh
hachota hi tamut, the soul that sins, he will die. בן לא
ישא בעוון האב, ben lo yisa ba'avon ha'av, the son will not
be held accountable for the sin of the father, obviously playing off
the פסוק about פוקד עוון אבות על בנים, poked avon avot al
banim, but here the פסוק in יחזקאל Yechezkel says no, it's going
to be just. אב לא ישא בעוון הבן, av lo yisa ba'avon
haben, the father won't be punished for
the sin of the son.
צדקת הצדיק עליו תהיה ורשעת הרשע עליו תהיה, tzidkat hatzadik alav tihyeh
v'rish'at harasha alav tihyeh, person will have their righteousness and the wicked
of the wicked person will be his. Nobody suffers for anybody else.
So that's but הנפש החוטאת, hanefesh hachota, only if it's a sinning
soul will it die. אין ייסורין בלא עוון, ein yissurin belo avon,
דכתיב ופקדתי בשבט פשעם, dechtiv upakadeti b'shevet pish'am, I will visit their
sin with the rod, ובנגעים עוונם, ubinega'im avonam, and their iniquity with
afflictions. מיתיבי, metivei, so the גמרא says I'll ask you on this.
אמרו מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amru mal'achei hasharet lifnei Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, Master of the Universe,
מפני מה קנסת מיתה על אדם הראשון? mipnei ma kanasta mita al
Adam HaRishon? Why did you say אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon had to
die? אמר להם, amar lahem, מצוה קלה צויתי ועבר עליה, mitzva kala
tziviti v'avar aleha, because I gave him an easy מצוה mitzva and
he transgressed it, so it brought about death. אמרו ליה, amru lei,
so they said to him, הלא משה ואהרן שקיימו כל התורה כולה
ומתו? halo Moshe v'Aharon shekiyemu kol HaTorah kulla umetu?
How about משה Moshe and אהרן, Aharon,
they fulfilled the whole תורה,
why did they have to die?
אמר ליה, amar lei, מקרה אחד לצדיק ולרשע לטוב, mikreh echad latzadik
velarasha latov, okay, everybody has one, you know, one end whether you're
righteous or wicked, or, you know, good or evil, everybody's going to
die. So yeah, maybe they were blameless, but once there's death, there's
death in the world. So who- sar- ah you see that there
is מיתה בלא עוון. mita belo avon. So the גמרא says wait
a minute, הוא דאמר כי האי תנא, hu d'amar ki hai tanna,
he goes like the other תנא, tanna, דתניא, d'tanya, we've done ברייתא,
braisa, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר אף משה ואהרן בחטא מתו. Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer af Moshe v'Aharon b'chet metu. No, they died
as a result of their sin. נאמר יען לא האמנתם בי, ne'emar
ya'an lo hemantem bi, because you did not believe in me. הא
האמנתם בי, ha hemantem bi, if you believed in me, במי מריבה,
b'mei Meriva, עדיין לא היה זמנכם ליפטר מן העולם, adayin lo haya
zmanchem l'ipater min ha'olam, you would not die, you would have continued
living. Now the obvious question is how could the other one say
they had no sin? They did have the sin, they didn't go
into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael So the גמרא basically explains, which I
think is pretty clear from the גמרא, that that might have been
enough that justified them not going into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, but
not enough that justified them dying. Even the position that says אין
מיתה בלא עוון ein mita belo avon doesn't mean that the tiniest
עוון avon merits dying. It means that the death will somehow be
justified because of the sin, בלא חטא, belo cheit, excuse me, ייסורין
בלא עוון. yissurin belo avon. It will somehow be justified. So the
first opinion says that חטא cheit was enough for them not to
go into ארץ ישראל, it would not have justified their death, and
the other opinion says yes it did justify their death. So here's
this debate of whether there is death without... without sin and ייסורין
yissurin without עוון, avon, without iniquity. Now partly this is an important
question about the general issue that we saw in the beginning of
ברכות, Brachot, you know, צדיק ורע לו רשע וטוב לו, tzadik v'ra
lo rasha v'tov lo, you know, is the world completely just or
does God allow natural causes, whether it's suffering or death, to occur
without it always factoring into a perfect שכר ועונש s'char v'onesh calculus?
That stuff will be worked out in עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, it
doesn't mean things in this world work out according to that. So
that's a general question, how much do we expect justice in this
world or once natural realities exist, hurricanes and, you know, and illness
and death, that's just the way the world works. There also could
be here also a sort of subtextual, sort of debate going on,
not debate, whatever, what's the word I'm looking for, polemic against... against
Christianity, right, that says that there's death because of original sin. So
here the גמרא holds out two alternatives. Either there's death because there's
death and it's not because of any sin, or because you sinned,
but there's no- but not because of like original sin. Death has-
that is what death is connected to. So this is the debate
about whether there is death without sin. So let's see as the
גמרא continues. מיתיבי, metivei, I'll ask you on this. ארבעה מתו בעטיו
של נחש, arba'a metu b'eyto shel nachash, four died because of as
a result of the נחש nachash or because of the... sort of
advice of because of the seduction of the נחש, nachash, questioning exactly
what that word means. ואלו הן, v'eilu hen, and these are they:
בנימין בן יעקב, Binyamin ben Yaakov, בנימין Binyamin the son of יעקב,
Yaakov, ועמרם אבי משה, v'Amram avi Moshe, עמרם Amram משה's father, וישי
אבי דוד, v'Yishai avi David, ישי Yishai דוד's David father, וכלאב בן
דוד, v'Kil'av ben David, כלאב Kil'av the son of דוד. David. Now
you'll notice that none of these are people we know anything about
and are not on central stage. And that might have to do
with the fact that if you want to live a life without
sin, so fine, then you have to totally remove yourself from this
world. Okay, if you're going to actually be involved in this world
and try to do something, then there'll be some sin that will
be involved. If you want to just take care of yourself, you
can go ahead and be a, you know, and go into some,
you know... Okay, but these four died without sin. וכולא גמרא, V'chula
Gemara, all of this we know by tradition, לבר מישי אבי דוד
דמפרש בקרא, L'var mi-Yishai avi David d'mefarash bikra, but Yishai, that's explicit.
You'll see how explicit it is. דכתיב, Dichtiv, as it is written:
ואת עמשא שם אבשלום תחת יואב, V'et Amasa sam Avshalom tachat Yoav,
Amasa, Avshalom made under Yoav, שר הצבא sar hatzava or על הצבא,
al hatzava, over the army, ועמשא בן איש ושמו יתרא הישראלי, V'Amasa
ben ish ushmo Yitra ha-Yisraeli, and Amasa was the son of a
man and his name was Yitra the Israeli, אשר בא אל אביגיל,
asher ba el Avigail, so he was the son of this man
Yitra who came to Abigail, who had a child with Abigail, and
who was Abigail? בת נחש, bat Nachash, the daughter of Nachash, אחות
צרויה, achot Tzeruya, the sister of Tzeruya, אם יואב, em Yoav, the
mother of Yoav. Now, the Gemara says: וכי בת נחש הויא והלא
בת ישי הויא? V'chi bat Nachash havaya v'halo bat Yishai havaya? Was
Abigail the daughter of Nachash? Abigail was the daughter of Yishai! דכתיב,
Dichtiv, it says by the brothers, the sons of Yishai: ואחיותיהם צרויה
ואביגיל, V'achyoteihem Tzeruya v'Avigail, and their sisters were Tzeruya and Abigail. So
here you have the same people, Tzeruya and Abigail, mentioned here and
mentioned by the daughters of Nachash. So Nachash seems to be a
name for Yishai. אלא בת מי שמת בעטיו של נחש. Ela bat
mi she-met b'ityo shel nachash. So why is Yishai called Nachash? Because
Yishai only died because of the sin of because of the nachash,
not because of his own sin. So the Gemara says: מאני, Mani,
who is this? אילימא, Ilima, by the way, also, assuming there is
some polemic with Christianity, you know, it's saying that it's all because
of the sin of the Garden of Eden, right? Gets makes me
evocative idea of like original sin. But it doesn't say they died
because of Adam, because of Adam's sin. They died because of the
nachash, you know. I understand, but the point is, is that it
seems to be dealing with the same issue, but you know, they're
whether consciously or not, clearly a different, you know, not allowing for
that possibility. So מאני, Mani, who is this? אילימא תנא דמלאכי השרת?
Ilima tana d'malachei hashareit? So this position that you said that only
four died without sin, who is the one that says this position?
If it's the story before about Moshe and Aaron, והאיכא משה ואהרן,
v'ika Moshe v'Aharon, you wouldn't have said four, you would have said
six, because you have Moshe and Aaron. אלא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר.
Ela Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. It must be Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
that disagreed and said Moshe and Aaron died by their sin, and
nevertheless here it's saying that there were four who didn't die as
a result of sin. ושמע מינה יש מיתה בלא חטא. U'shma mina
yeish mita b'lo cheit. Even those that say Moshe died as a
result of sin would still say in general I agree it's possible
to die without sin. ויש יסורין בלא עון. V'yeish yissurin b'lo avon.
And it's possible, although that wasn't really discussed or proven either way,
but if one is true, presumably the other. It's possible to suffer
without sin. תיובתא דרב אמי תיובתא, Tiyuvta d'Rav Ami tiyuvta, and this
is a complete contradiction of Rav Ami. Now that's pretty strong because
the Gemara, Rav Ami was the one that says that it always
happens as a result of sin. So this is evidently very powerful
in the context of the discussion, you know, in Brachot about tzadik
v'ra lo and so on, that this Gemara seems to end pretty
with some finality that there is suffering in this world that's not
always attributable to justice and to s'char v'onesh, and you know, God
will work it out however God works it out, but there's also
the natural way in which the world works. Which, you know, for
us I think very much conforms to, you know, a sort of
our modern sensibility. Is it comforting or not comforting? You know, it
doesn't say that's always the way, it doesn't say there's no justice,
just that that's a part of the world. Anyway, other Gemaras don't
necessarily adopt this even though this Gemara seems to end with some
finality. Let's just read the next let's get a little bit further.
אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני. Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani. We're doing
a lot of theological issues here. אמר רבי יונתן: Amar Rabbi Yonatan:
כל האומר ראובן חטא אינו אלא טועה. Kol ha-omer Reuven chata eino
ela to'eh. Anybody that says Reuven sinned, because we're dealing about did
people sin or not and what you know and Moshe and Aaron,
anybody that says Reuven sinned is only making a mistake. שנאמר ויהיו
בני יעקב שנים עשר. She-ne'emar vayihyu venei Ya'akov shneim asar. Right after
it says that Reuven slept with Bilhah, it says the sons of
Jacob were twelve. Why does it say that immediately after right in
the middle of the pasuk? מלמד שכולם שקולים כאחת. Melamed she-kulam shekulim
k'echat. They were all equivalent, they were all righteous. אלא מה אני
מקיים? Ela ma ani mekayem? So what do I do with the
pasuk: וישכב את בלהה פילגש אביו? Vayishkav et Bilhah pilegesh aviv? He
slept with Bilhah, his father's concubine. מלמד שבלבל מצעו של אביו. Melamed
she-bilbel matzo shel aviv. He didn't sleep with her, he messed up
his father's bed, he upturned it or whatever, we'll see why in
a minute. ומעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו שכב עמה. U'ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu
shakhav imah. Because he got in the way of his father sleeping
with Bilhah and he got involved, you know, and intervened and you
know sort of injected himself there, so that was as if he
was sleeping with her. תניא, Tanya, we learn in a baraita: רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר: Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer: מוצל אותו צדיק
מעוון זה. Mutzal oto tzadik me-avon zeh. That righteous person Reuven, who
you know who we even know what he did to save Yosef,
he was saved from that sin. Maybe he was saved, that's an
interesting phrase he was saved, sounds like maybe he wanted to but
in the end he didn't. Anyway, he didn't do that sin. ולא
בא מעשה זה לידו. V'lo ba ma'aseh zeh l'yado. That seems even
further, it didn't even get come close to doing this action. אפשר
עתיד זרעו לעמוד על הר עיבל ולומר? Efshar atid zaro la'amod al
Har Eival v'lomar? His children will eventually stand on Har Eival, Reuven's
tribe stands on Har Eival, you know, and they are the ones
that say half the tribes say the klalah and half say the
brachah. So his tribe... Is it possible that that was what's going
to happen to his descendants, ויהא חטא לידו, v'yei cheit l'yado, and
God would have allowed him to sin on this very matter or
this would have happened? אלא מאי, Ella mai, so what do I
do with that פסוק, מה אני מקיים וישכב את בלהה פילגש אביו?
ma ani mekayem Vayishkav es Bilhah pilegesh aviv? עלבון אמו תבע. elbon
imo tava. He came to defend the injustice against his mother, the
insult to his mother. אמר, he said, look, אמה אחות אמי, ima
achos imi, thank you, הייתה צרה לאמי. hayesa tzarah l'imi. So if,
if my, if my mother's sister, רחל, Rachel, was, you know, was
the competitor wife with לאה, Leah, fine, that's I'm not happy with,
but I could have understood. But now רחל Rachel is dead. And
so שפחת אחות אמי, shifchas achos imi, my, my mother's sister's servant,
slave, תהא צרה לאמי? t'hei tzarah l'imi? That's going to take my
mother's place? She's going to take my mother's place? How could it
be that יעקב Yaakov is now favoring בלהה? Bilhah? What about my
mother? אלא, so what'd he do? עמד ובלבל את מצעה. amad ubilbel
es matzah. He went and he overturned or whatever, you know, messed
up her, her bed. You know, he was there to defend his
mother and that's why he got involved. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, others
say, שתי מצעות בלבל. shtei matza'os bilbel. He messed up two beds.
אחת של שכינה, achas shel Shechinah, one of the Divine Presence, ואחת
של אביו, v'achas shel aviv, one of his father's. והיינו דכתיב, v'hainu
d'chsiv, so not her bed, his father's bed. והיינו v'hainu and the
שכינה. Shechinah. דכתיב, D'chsiv, אז חללת יצועי עלה, az chillalta y'tzu'i alah,
then you desecrated, so חלול chillul is the same we associate with
God, and my bed עלה, alah, not עלית alisa but עלה. alah.
So רש״י Rashi says my bed that the שכינה Shechinah went on
my bed. So רש״י Rashi says that there was an idea that
the שכינה Shechinah was in the tent of the צדיקים, Tzadikim, you
know, before there was a משכן. Mishkan. And he also says that
almost like יעקב Yaakov put a bed to represent the presence of
the שכינה, Shechinah, which is a fascinating idea. So wherever יעקב Yaakov
was going to sleep that night, רש״י Rashi says he put up
a bed to represent, you know, that the שכינה Shechinah would be
present, which fits into גמרות Gemaras about, you know, איש and אשה
ishah and God present between husband and wife even, you know, at
the most intimate moments. So when יעקב Yaakov went in, he not
only destroyed, I mean ראובן, Reuven you know, messed up יעקב'ס Yaakov's
bed, but the שכינה'ס Shechinah's bed as well to say maybe that
God should have no part in this, whatever it was according to
this understanding. But he didn't sleep with her. So let's just finish
this. כתנאי, K'tanna'i, like the related תנאים. Tanna'im. פחז כמים אל תותר.
pachaz kamayim al totar. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, פסעתה חבתה
זלתה. pasa'ta chavta zalta. No, actually he did sin. פחז Pachaz is
like ראשי תיבות, rashei teivos, you were, you were impetuous, you sinned,
and you, and you, you know, חבתה chavta is in חוב? chov?
חוב, Chov, right. And זלתה zalta and you, you know, you, you
denigrated. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, פסעתה על דת, pasa'ta al
das, you stepped over the, the faith, the religion, חטאת, chatasa, you
sinned, זנית, zanisa, you committed adultery. So clearly they say he sinned.
רבן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Gamliel omer, לא. lo. פללת, Pillalta, you prayed
to God, חלת, chalta, you, you know, you, you importuned, זרחה תפילתך.
zarchah tfilasecha. So and your, your prayers were shown, you actually saved,
so maybe you wanted to sin, but you asked God for help,
for strength to withhold you and you didn't. Why אל תותר? al
totar? I don't know, because he still got involved. אמר רבן גמליאל,
Amar Rabban Gamliel, עדיין צריכין אנו למודעי, adayin tzrichin anu l'Moda'i, we
still need מודעי, Moda'i, which is the רבי אליעזר המודעי Rabbi Eliezer
HaModa'i who they thought was excellent in אגדתא. Aggadeta רבי אליעזר המודעי
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer HaModa'i omer, הפוך את התיבה ודורשה, hafoch es hateivah
v'dorshah, read it backwards. Not פ-ח-ז, peh-ches-zayin, ז-ח-פ. zayin-ches-peh. זעזעת, Ziazata, you
trembled, חרדת, chiradta, you also you shook because you were maybe trying
to sin and you were struggling with your better nature, ופרחה חטא
ממך, u'farchah cheit mimcha, and then the sin flew away from you,
you succumbed, you know, but you, you, you know, you, you succeeded,
you, I'm sorry, overcame. Overcame, thank you, the opposite, you overcame your
evil desire. חזרת לתקנך. chazarta l'siknecha. Right. רבא אומר, Rava omer, yes.
רבא, Rava, good point. רבא אומר ואמרי לה רבי ירמיה בר אבא,
Rava omer v'amri lah Rabbi Yirmeyah bar Abba, זכרת עונשו של דבר,
zacharta onsho shel davar, also reading reverse, you remembered the, the punishment
you'll get if you'll sin, so maybe it's not just, you know,
because it's wrong but because of the punishment. חלית עצמך חולי גדול,
chalis atzmecha choli gadol, you made yourself sick, you know, struggling with
your evil desire and your desire to do the right thing, פירשת
ממלאכתך, pirashta mimalachtecha, and in the end you managed to separate yourself
from sin. So the גמרא will continue tomorrow with the question about
people that it looks like in תנ״ך Tanach sinned that the גמרא
is going to say didn't sin, but it's important to remember that
the גמרא actually here quotes different opinions, and some actually say that
ראובן did sin. You know, when שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz came out with his
book, Biblical Images, you know, and he described things pretty much according
to פשט, you know, he was put in חרם cherem by, by
רב שך Rav Shach because oh my god, how could you say
these great figures of תנ״ך Tanach did these terrible things? But so
okay, the גמרא'ס Gemara's that's one approach, right, but there's the other
approach is, first of all, you know, already in the גמרא that
no, they did do what it says, and you know, there's always
been this tension between אגדתא and פשוטו של מקרא pishuto shel mikra
and אין מקרא יוצא מידי פשוטו. ein mikra yotzei midei pshuto. So
anyway, we will continue seeing this discussion about great people who sinned
or do not sin tomorrow.